<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>England bought and sold, or, A discovery of a horrid design to destroy the antient liberty of all the free-holders in England, in the choice of members to serve in the Honourable House of Commons in Parliament, by a late libel entituled, The certain way to save England, &amp;c.</title>
            <author>Nalson, John, 1638?-1686.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A52220</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N101</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10091</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13111367</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13111367</idno>
            <idno type="VID">97679</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A52220)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97679)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 746:30)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>England bought and sold, or, A discovery of a horrid design to destroy the antient liberty of all the free-holders in England, in the choice of members to serve in the Honourable House of Commons in Parliament, by a late libel entituled, The certain way to save England, &amp;c.</title>
                  <author>Nalson, John, 1638?-1686.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for T.O.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>England and Wales. --  Parliament.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:97679:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>England Bought and Sold:</hi> OR, A DISCOVERY OF A HORRID DESIGN TO Deſtroy the Antient Liberty Of all the FREE-HOLDERS IN ENGLAND, In the Choice of MEMBERS to Serve IN THE Honourable Houſe of Commons IN PARLIAMENT.</p>
            <p>By a Late Libel Entituled, <hi>The Certain Way to Save</hi> ENGLAND, <hi>&amp;c,</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PROV. xvi. 28.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>A Tale-bearer maketh Strife, and a Whiſperer ſeparateth chiefeſt Friends.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON: Printed for <hi>T. O.</hi> 1681.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:97679:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:97679:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>England</hi> bought and ſold, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THERE was never any Deſign ſo black and Criminous, but found ſome perſons ſo Profligate, as to become its Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons; there wanted not an <hi>Iſcariot</hi> for Thirty pieces of Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, to betray his Maſter, nor a popular pretence, <hi>ſaving of the State,</hi> leſt the
<hi>Romans ſhould come, and take away their Place, and Nation,</hi> to put the better colour upon the Murder of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our: And a nearer Inſtance will abundantly refreſh our Memories, without more than the trouble of remembring <hi>Jan.</hi> 30. 1648.</p>
            <p>The worſt Surfeits are taken by the moſt luſhious Fruits, and no Poyſon can be ſo dangerous, as that which has the name of an <hi>Antidote</hi> written upon the Box. There was never any miſchief in State or Kingdom, but the People were firſt drawn in to believe, that the Projectors were their Friends, and then thoſe Juglers pre-poſſeſs them with falſe apprehenſions of things, and undertake to redreſs all their Grievances. They are prodigal in their fair Promiſes, and flattering Speeches, like <hi>Abſalom,</hi> when they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the fouleſt Enterprizes.</p>
            <p>Certainly, the happineſs of a People conſiſts in Peace, which is the Mother of all deſirables of this World, and Peace moſt certainly depends upon the due Subjection, and Obedience of the People to their Sovereign, and the wiſe and wholſome eſtabliſhments of Laws. And therefore they who deſign to ſubvert the one, or diſturb the other, always repreſent the Laws uneaſie, or the Sovereign unjuſt, and apply their whole endeavours to create, foment, and increaſe Miſ-underſtandings between the Prince and his People.</p>
            <p>Whoever goes about to divorce theſe two, whom God hath joyned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, ought to be reputed an Enemy to both, a betrayer of his Country, and a moſt dangerous Incendiary, a peſtilent Fellow, and a mover of Sedition.</p>
            <p>Now, as the greateſt Artifice is to conceal the Act, ſo I find the Author of this Libel, by which he pretends to ſave <hi>England,</hi> ſo great a Maſter in the Talent of deceiving, that he might have been Tutor, as he is, certainly the Scholar, to that old guilded Serpent, who deceived <hi>Eve.</hi> For he has not planted his Battery againſt any particular part of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, That would have been too viſible, but he has undermined the very Foundation, and has endeavoured to ſpoil the whole frame, not by open breaking the whole, but by altering the weights, which keep the Move<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment right, and in due order.</p>
            <p>He has firſt violated the greateſt Priviledge of the People of <hi>England,</hi> indeavouring to rob them of that ancient right, liberty and freedom of Election of perſons to repreſent them in Parliament, impoſing upon them by the ſpecious way of Advice, Reſtrictions, Limitations, Rules and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections in their Choice.</p>
            <p>Secondly, He has violated the priviledge and honour of the Commons-Houſe in Parliament, who have ever endeavoured to have their Reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſecured by the freedom of the Election of their Members. And I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:97679:3"/>that even the Commons of that Parliament of <hi>November</hi> the Third, 1640. who are ſufficiently memorable, and poſſibly, for which this Libeller has a veneration, when ſome great Lords only writ a Letter Recommendatory about the Election of an inconſiderable Burrough, vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it a high breach of Priviledge: And yet our pert Libeller, or Legion, for any thing I know has had the confidence to write, and for expedition to Print a Letter Recommendatory, and diſperſe it to all the Counties, and Cities, Burroughs and Corporations of
<hi>England,</hi> thereby to foreſtal the Elections; One of which Letters, by miſtaking his perſon came to be diſcovered, and you ſhall preſently ſee the Tenor of it.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, He has by many falſe, diſloyal, not to ſay traiterous Inſinuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, indeavoured to defame His Sacred Majeſty, and the eſtabliſhed Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and to bring a general <hi>Odium</hi> upon both, thereby to alienate the affections of the People from their natural Liege-Lord, to the impair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his Honour, Juſtice and Wiſdom, the great ſupporters of his Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Scepter, Crown, and Dignity.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, He has indeavoured to heighten the preſent unhappy miſ-un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings, and to poſſeſs the People with Fears, Terrors and diſmal Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions of I know not what Deſpotick power, Tyranny and Arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Government that is coming in upon them, and that their ALL, Lives, Liberties, Religion, and Eſtates are at Stake, with ſuch fulſomly Rebellious reflections upon the King and Government, as may animate the People by a deſperate effort of Sedition to Rebel againſt their moſt Gracious Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, He has cunningly aſperſed, and vilified a great number of His Majeſties moſt Dutiful, and Loyal Subjects of all Orders, and Ranks as Enemies to the Kingdom, Pentioners, Courtiers, romoters of a Popiſh Intereſt, and Succeſſion, and defames by whole-Sale many worthy Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of moſt approved Loyalty and Fidelity to their King, and ſound principles in the Proteſtant Religion as by Law Eſtabliſhed, thereby to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capacitate them from being Elected to ſerve their King and Countrey as Members of Parliament; by rendring them ſuſpected, and odious to the Electors: And indeed the whole drift of the Libel, is to prevent ſuch as are of known Integrity to the King, and the Church from coming into the next Houſe of Commons, and to perſuade them to chooſe Men of <hi>large</hi> Principles as he calls them, which I need not I think explain for he does it himſelf, as you ſhall ſee hereafter.</p>
            <p>This is a great and heavy charge, but I will make it out true to a Tittle, and yet ſhall draw but a few ſtrictures upon a Libel, for which at ſome times the Author would not only have loſt his Ears, but hazarded the Head, that framed it, and let him have a care, Juſtice, and the Vengeance both of Heaven, and of Kings that have long Arms.</p>
            <p>The Letter will make good the firſt and ſecond Articles, and the Book both them, and all the reſt. The Letter was ſuperſcribed, and ſent by the Poſt, and has the Poſt-mark,
<hi>Feb.</hi> 5. ſtamped upon it, but the Contents to the Surprize of many worthy Gentlemen, to whom they were directed were in Print, as follows,</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:97679:3"/>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THere is newly publiſhed a ſmall ſtitched Book well worth the ſerious peru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal of all your Electors, and I think if you would put your ſelf to the ſmall charge of buying a parcel of them for your Countrey People, It may be one great means of keeping them tight and ſteddy in their Choice of good Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants and true <hi>Engliſhmen,</hi> for their Members in the next enſuing Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whereupon depends the <hi>Weal</hi> or <hi>Woe</hi> both of King and Kingdom, not only in this, but in future Ages; It has compriſed in it, all the material things that were in any of the former ſheets upon the ſame Subject, and gives you additional ones that are at preſent moſt neceſſary to be conſidered. In this Juncture of Affairs we are now in, it is thought (by thoſe that have ſeen and examined it) that there cannot be a more ready ſerviceable Book to publick uſe and benefit, than this that is offered you, by</p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>Sir,</salute>
                     <signed>A hearty well Wiſher of the Proſperity and Happineſs of the King and Kingdom.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The Title of the Book is, <hi>The certain way to ſave</hi> England, <hi>not only now, but in future Ages, by a prudent Choice of Members to ſerve in the next Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, in a ſeaſonable Addreſs to the Freeholders, and other Electors,</hi> Sold by <hi>Richard Baldwin</hi> in
<hi>Ball-Court</hi> in the <hi>Old Baily, price</hi> Six pence.</p>
            <p>If to Calculate the Nativity of the King, be thought ſo dangerous a Preſumption, as by Law to be adjudged Felony during Q. <hi>Elizabeths</hi> Life, what may we think of the Crime of this Conjurer, who gives ſo poſitive a Judgment of King, Parliament and Kingdom, pronouncing Magiſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally the future Fate of <hi>England;</hi> Upon the Elections (ſays he) depends the Weal or Woe both of King and Kingdom, not only in this,<note place="margin">Vide Co. 3 Inſt. f. 6. De vita Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipis inquire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re preſertim per aſtrologos capitale: ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que hoc ſolum ſed etiam de ea dubitare vel deſperare pro crimine Majeſtatis laeſae habitum eſſe; ſi indiciis eſſet aliquibus ea deſperatio pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tefacta. ſcip. Gentil. lib. 1. de Conjurati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one.</note> but future Ages; But the beſt on't is, He is but like the reſt of that Tribe, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ignorant of their own Deſtiny, yet will pretend to Propheſie of other Perſons; And I hope
<hi>England</hi> will, when he is either forgotten, or only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred for Infamy, ſee many Wiſe, Prudent and Loyal Parliaments.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>p.</hi> 4.</note>He prefaces his Diſcourſe with the popular Theme of the <hi>Horrid Popiſh Plot,</hi> upon which he lays a Load, not more than it deſerves, but that is not ſo much to run down the Papiſts, as to ſerve a Turn, which afterwards he diſcovers, and is ſo hot upon it, that his Patience would not give him leave to tell it out, without a neceſſary <hi>Parentheſis</hi> againſt the Biſhops, whom like Traiterous
<hi>Joab,</hi> he Salutes and Stabs at the ſame time: For, ſays he,
<q rend="margQuotes">'the Papiſts had a Deſign to remove and deprive all Proteſtant Biſhops, and other Eccleſiaſtical Perſons (and God knows what a number there is of them in this Nation) from their Offices, Benefices and Preferments, One would think this a vindication of the Biſhops, and Clergy;</q> but leſt he ſhould do them a ſervice, in comes a malitious
<hi>Parentheſis</hi> in a <hi>Roman</hi> Letter, and with a <hi>Romiſh</hi> Deſign, (and God knows, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) Why, Sir and do not you know too? Have you never read Dr. <hi>Oates</hi>'s Depoſitions, he makes them all Proteſtant Biſhops, but though you and your Party, who may Defame the Kings Evidence, <hi>Cum Privilegio,</hi> Two years ago would but allow two Proteſtant Biſhops, and one you ſay is fallen off ſince; and for the Clergy, they are all Tantivies, and Popiſhly affected, as you per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuade
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:97679:4"/>the People. And the <hi>Parentheſis</hi> in a different Letter is deſigned for a Remark upon them, leſt ſome of your Party ſhould miſtake you.</p>
            <p>But that which ſurpriſed me, was the Impudence of the Man, who at the ſame time when he juſtly charges thoſe Helliſh and Execrable Plotters with the guilt of endeavouring to rob the King of his Royal Crown and Dignity, by malicious, and unadviſed ſpeaking, writing, and otherwiſe, he himſelf was adviſedly doing the ſame, and with one or two more Ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravations, Printing, Publiſhing, and diſperſing this ſeditious Libel againſt the King and Kingdom; but becauſe though a man ſees all other Mens Faces, but never his own without a Glaſs, I preſent him this, which will tell him his Face as well as his Pen hath been in the Ink-pot,</p>
            <p>In the next page he addreſſes himſelf to the People, and the more to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timidate them,<note place="margin">Pag. 5.</note> thereby to prepare them for his following Impreſſions, he paints their danger with all the terrible Aſpects, which his Art can invent to render it more formidable; and in ſhort, informs them, that their ALL is now in hazard, and that Self-preſervation exacts from them not to ſuffer any, but who he adviſes them to be Elected into any places of Office or Truſt within this Kingdom. Now firſt I obſerve, that he never qualifies this principle of Self-preſervation, with any Limitation of doing what we lawfully may do in order to the preſervation either of our ſelves or our ALL, and indeed he is a man of large principles, <hi>Quicquid libet licet,</hi> I ſuppoſe is one of them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, It is to be obſerved, that he never tells the People, how ſolici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous the King is for their Safety, how he hath done all that poſſibly he can to ſecure the Nation, turned out all the Popiſh Lords out of the Houſe of Peers, diſarmed all the Papiſts throughout
<hi>England,</hi> Married the Lady <hi>Mary</hi> to a Proteſtant Prince to ſecure the Succeſſion, permitted the Law to have its full and free ſcope againſt all the Conſpirators of what degree ſoever, hath importuned the Parliament for the vigorous and ſpeedy Tryal, and Proſecution of the Popiſh Lords, and though he hath not been treated with ſuch deference as a Prince, who never denyed his Subjects any thing but one, might have expected, yet ſtill he continues his care of his People. But not a ſyllable of this muſt the People hear, but on the contrary two moſt malicious Reflections upon the Crown, where he tells them ſuch Members as he is about to adviſe them to Elect, will [maintain all the Kings juſt Honours and Prerogatives] this word <hi>juſt,</hi> is a ſuſpicious word, It is juſt ſuch a word as was in the late Solemn League and Covenant, and is to give the People to underſtand the King hath ſome Honours and Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives which are not juſt. And for fear this Hint ſhould not be powerful enough; he treads upon their Toes again with another happy <hi>Parentheſis,</hi> and tells them how they will maintain theſe juſt Honours; by taking away our great and many (I cannot ſay how well or ill-grounded) fears and jealouſies of Arbitrary Government. Well then, if you cannot ſay how well or ill-grounded, why do you ſay it at all? and if you can ſay, why ſo ſqueamiſh all of a ſudden? I tell you Sir, you will run the hazard of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing more Knave and Fool, a Knave to ſay a thing you cannot juſtifie, and a Fool for ſo plainly ſhewing your ſelf a Knave, when it was your great Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt to have paſſed currant for a Man of ſuperfine Honeſty. And I muſt aſſure you this flaw in your Credit, and a Crack of your own free volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary and uncompelled making, will render your Reputation ſuſpicious in whatever you ſay hereafter.</p>
            <p>Then he paſſes on to his Qualifications, which if he had left in their Scripture Purity, without the Gloſſary of an Author in his Margent, who
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:97679:4"/>dedicated his Labors the ſucking Uſurper <hi>Richard, quondam</hi> Protector, they would have been much better reliſhed by Perſons of Loyalty.</p>
            <p>To paſs by his limping paraphraſe upon the firſt, Men that fear God, <hi>i.e.</hi> Halt not between two opinions, which yet is not without its deſign againſt all thoſe Gentlemen, who are zealous for the preſent Eſtabliſhment in the Church, who are ever repreſented to the People as halting between God and <hi>Baal,</hi> Popery and Proteſtantiſm, and in that ſenſe incapacitated by this Gentleman for Repreſentatives of the Commons of <hi>England:</hi> His Second Comment is ſtollen from the late Rebel-Parliament, who are very ill Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terns for the People to chooſe by. Loving Truth, <hi>i. e.</hi> Such as the King and Kingdom may truſt. All they did in the late Rebellion was for the good of the King and Kingdom; they choſe into the Parliament all that could be pickt up that had manifeſted any Animoſity againſt the King or His Government, for the good of the King and Kingdom; they diſplaced all His Friends under the notion of Evil Counſellors, for the good of the King and Kingdom; and they raiſed an Army againſt the King under the Earl of <hi>Eſſex</hi> for the good of the King and Kingdom; they fought againſt him in the Field, and Bullets flew as thick as Hail about His Head for the good of the King and Kingdom, and in fine, they cut off His glorious Head too for the good of the King and Kingdom.</p>
            <p>And for the Third, hating Covetouſneſs, he is quite by the Cuſhion with his <hi>i. e.</hi> For it clearly intimates that they ſhould chearfully aſſiſt their Sovereign with neceſſary Aids, Subſidies, and Supplies: But he knows what hath gone abroad of late as a State-Maxim <hi>If upon any Terms we part with our Money, till we are ſure the King is ours, the Nation is betrayed.</hi> And yet <hi>Cicero</hi> a better Orator, I cannot ſay a greater Common-wealths Man, poſitively affirms <hi>Imperium ſine vectigalibus retineri nullo modo poteſt:</hi> which it is to be feared is the true foundation of the fore-recited Maxim.</p>
            <p>And becauſe this Adviſer, like the Jeſuits, doth not think the Scripture a ſufficient Rule: He proceeds to lay down Truths and Counſels as plain as poſſible he can, and by his Recommendatory Letter he would have his Traditions make out the Inſuffciency and Obſcurity of Old <hi>Jethro</hi>'s Rules, who being a Prieſt or a Prince, or both, may be thought too much inclining to the Court Party, as I ſuppoſe <hi>Solomon</hi> and St. <hi>Peter</hi> for the ſame Reaſons are quite omitted, or otherwiſe thoſe who <hi>(Fear God, and Honour the King, and meddle not with ſuch as are given to change, whoſe Calamity ariſeth ſuddenly, and who knows the Ruin of them both?)</hi> might have bid fairly to have been admitted for ſuch Counſellors in whoſe mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude the ſafety of King and People too conſiſts.</p>
            <p>And now this Quack State-Doctor begins to talk learnedly of Critical Days, and times, and I pray conſider, ſays he, this is a Critical Time, upon your well or ill chuſing depends your well or ill Being: and you had need to do that well which you do not know, whether ever you may do again. Your Fate may not ſuffer you to offend twice in this one Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular. Indeed this is an Amazing Paragraph: This Fellow is the very Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of the Conſult of the Jeſuits at
<hi>Wild-Houſe,</hi> as Doctor <hi>Oats</hi> in his Narrative Depoſes, That they intended to effect their wicked Plot <hi>Pag.</hi> 67. by diſaffecting the Kings beſt Friends, and Subjects. <hi>Firſt,</hi> Charging him with Tyranny and Deſigns of Oppreſſing, Governing by the Sword, and without Parliaments. <hi>Secondly,</hi> By aſperſing, Deriding, Expoſing, and Declaiming againſt His Perſon, Councils and Actions in Parliament, and elſewhere. Nothing but the Impudence of a Plotter, ſuch a one as the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:97679:5"/>Doctor deſcribes, could give the Lye to Majeſty. The King aſſures His People he will meet them in frequent Parliaments, and here comes an Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſer to tell the People they do not know, whether they may ever chuſe Members for Parliaments again, that their Fate may not ſuffer them to offend twice in that one Particular; which is only in ſofter words the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to deceive the People, to promote the Popiſh Plot by perſuading the Nation they are like to have no more Parliaments.</p>
            <p>Theſe two Paragraphs of Doctor <hi>Oats</hi> which I have mentioned, are in truth the Contents of his whole Book, and the Libel is only an cularge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon theſe two heads of the Plot: And if that be the way to Save <hi>England,</hi> God deliver all good Proteſtants from ſuch Savers and ſuch Salvation. And I deſire the Reader to carry theſe Expoſitors in his mind, for he ſhall find him all along indeavouring to traduce either the King or the Government or both; upon which he is ſo violently bent that he perſuades the People to whom for their Edification the Diſcourſe is addreſſed: That Kings have been their Conſtant Enemies; for, ſays he, Liberty and Property were reſcued by Inches out of the hands of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croaching Violence; and this is another of his ſtabbing parentheſes. When in truth the People owe all their Liberties, Franchiſes, Charters and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munities, and even that great one of Commons to repreſent them in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, to the Bounty, and Goodneſs of former Kings, and never any King either did or attempted to deprive the People of the Grants of their Predeceſſors. Let the Charter of
<hi>London</hi> now publickly Printed and Sold be looked into, and it will ſhew from
<hi>William</hi> the Conqueror, to His moſt Auguſt Majeſty King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, what vaſt favors the Kings of <hi>England</hi> have con-ferred upon that City, which it is to be hoped will incline them to Loyalty and Gratitude to His Majeſty, and to ſtop their Ears againſt ſuch Charming Seducers, as this and other Libellers; eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally if they remember that the firſt violaters of their Charter, and the great Charter of <hi>England</hi> were the late Uſurpers, who dethroned and murthered their Lawful King, by the very ſame popular Arts, the Fears and Jealouſies of Evil-Counſellors, and Arbitrary Government.</p>
            <p>Conſider, ſaith he, you truſt the Parliament with your Eſtates, Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Religion, and Lives. And do the People chuſe the Parliament too or only the Houſe of Commons? Are not the King and the Lords Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual and Temporal to be truſted? A late Libel has indeed ſaid <hi>we want a King and a Government that we may truſt,</hi> &amp;c. And now comes in our Commentator, and obtrudes the word Parliament, as if it only conſiſted of the Lower Houſe, and the whole truſt were in them, as preſently after he adds; they have the Intereſt and Charge of us all upon them. For, ſaith he, ſhould you be undone in any of theſe, when it's too late, you may lament, that you are undone by making ſuch a choice as hath undone you by Law. A fair proſecution of the Deſign and Plot mentioned by Doctor <hi>Oats,</hi> but that will not ſatisfie him, the man is for ſpeaking plain Truths and Counſels, and therefore he does it to purpoſe in the next page. How your Expectations have been fruſtrated, your hopes blaſted, you feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly bewail;<note place="margin">Pag. 9.</note> exactly as the Doctor ſaith, Expoſing and Declaiming againſt His Majeſties Perſon, Counſels, and Actions in Parlliament. For adds he, by what Counſels you have been defeated in the Diſſolution of Parliaments, you cannot be ignorant. And upon this, like <hi>Gavan</hi> at a Quakers Meeting, or <hi>Whitebread</hi> at a Conventicle, he falls a Canting, of what an excellent ſpirit was poured upon them in their laſt Elections; Even ſuch a ſpirit as fell upon the Jews Exorciſts, <hi>Acts</hi> xix. 16. which in ſome places inſpired the Diſſenters
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:97679:5"/>with ſuch Fury as to beat, wound, and kill thoſe, who oppoſed their Choice of ſuch as were in the Opinion of Diſſenters, particular Friends to their Opinions and Practices, or had been in Actual Arms againſt the late King and His preſent Majeſty.</p>
            <p>But he proceeds, and I muſt keep pace with him in his dirty Road, tho we travel to different Quarters: In his ſecond Qualification, They muſt be men throughly principled in the Proteſtant Religion; very good! and why could it not be added, as now by Law Eſtabliſhed; are the Lawleſs Proteſtants the beſt Proteſtants, and they who obey the Laws the worſt? We muſt come to diſtinction then I find, ſince the very word Porteſtant admits of Ambiguity. All lay claim to it, Quakers, who are no Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and Anabaptiſts who are very ill ones, and all others by what names ſoever dignified, or diſtinguiſhed, will all challenge the Name of Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants; which of theſe doth he mean, and what Proteſtant Principles thoſe of the Law Proteſtants, or Lawleſs Proteſtants: We ſhall not need to go far for a Reſolution, They are the <hi>large</hi> Principles that he means, ſuch as will not ſacrifice his Neighbours Property to the frowardneſs of his own Party in Religion. Now tho this is plainly level'd at ſuch Gentlemen as have in obedience to the Law, and diſcharge of their Conſciences proſecuted Diſſenters, not out of frowardneſs but neceſſity, as conſidering what a dangerous influence their pretences of Religion have had upon the State; yet in the next page, to clear his Counſel and Truth, and make it plain, you ſhall ſee a double portion of the excellent ſpirit of <hi>Ned Coleman,</hi> and of the late Lord <hi>Stafford</hi> poured upon him, when he tells the People,<note place="margin">Pag. 10.</note> That the great Intereſt of
<hi>England</hi> at this day is to tolerate the tolerable, to bear with the weak, to encourage the conſcientious, and to reſtrain none but ſuch as would reſtrain all beſides themſelves. Lo! here Toleration and Perſecution both in a breath: The Church of <hi>England</hi> becauſe by the help of the Secular Laws, ſhe endeavours to reſtrain men from run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to damnation, muſt be reſtrained her ſelf: This is ſo large a Goſpel-Principle as I am ſure Chriſt never taught. I would ask this <hi>vir quidam,</hi> whether he thinks Schiſm a damnable Sin or not? If not, then he hath neither Principles nor Religion; If he doth believe it ſo, let him read Doctor
<hi>Stilling fleet</hi>'s late Book, which hath ſufficiently convinced all Diſſenters to be Guilty of Schiſm. Would it not be great honour then for a Parliament to Eſtabliſh Iniquity by a Law, and is it then the great In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of <hi>England,</hi> that the People ſhould have an Act of Parliament, to damn themſelves by Authority. Sure this is Doctrine and Advice fit for none but Jeſuits and Devils to Preach. Good God! What will not ſome men do, to make a Party?</p>
            <p>His Third Qualification is, Men of Courage, who will not be Hector'd out of their Duty by the Frouns and Scouls of Men. Let him be who he will, he deſerves a ſevere Caſtigation for two things: <hi>Firſt,</hi> For want of due Reſpect, and Manners to his Superiors.
<hi>Secondly,</hi> For Charging them with ſuch Actions as they are not Guilty of. Why there is not the littleſt Fop about the Town but would think himſelf affronted with the name of Hector, and yet this piece of Inſolence fears not to pin it indefinitely upon the Higheſt Characters in the Nation.</p>
            <p>His Fourth is, Men of Reſolution that will ſtand by and maintain the Power and Priviledges of Parliament (for they are the Heart-ſtring of the Nation) Then Mr. Parentheſis you have broke the Heart-ſtrings of the Nation; for the Fundamental Priviledge of the Houſe of Commons is Freedome of Choice of the Members, of which Fraud and Force are
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:97679:6"/>equally deſtructive, and which both by your Letter and your Book, you have endeavoured to violate.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Men that will proſecute the Plot, and ſearch into the bottom of it. With all my heart; for by Dr. <hi>Oats</hi>'s Narrative, your Worſhip Sir, and all that are like you will be found there, and the Nation will never be at quiet, till ſuch fellows as you, who lie ſculking there be found out, and ſeverely puniſh'd.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, ſuch as will remove and bring to Juſtice Evil Counſellors. Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt and Arbitrary Miniſters of State, that have been ſo Induſtrious to give the King wrong Meaſures, to turn things out of their Antient and Legal Channel of Adminiſtration, and Alienate His Affections from His People. Sure the Man is beſides himſelf, did ever one take ſuch pains to make a ſilken Cravat for himſelf? Are you in ſerious Earneſt Sir? Would you have all that endeavour to breed miſunderſtandings between the King and His People ſeverely puniſh'd? Then are you in exceeding danger of the Fate of <hi>Haman,</hi> who built a pair of Gallows of fifty Cubits high for <hi>Mordecai;</hi> no man I will ſay that for you, hath taken more pains or indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured with more Art to alienate the Affections of the People from the King <hi>&amp; vice verſa,</hi> than you have done, and by your own Law you know what you deſerve. As for any other who have done as you ſay, His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty who hates all thoughts of Arbitrary Government, hath told you, He will leave them to the Law, and you ſhould have acquainted the People with that Juſt and Honourable Reſolution of His Majeſty, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>Magna Charta, Nec ibimus ſuper eum niſi per Legale Judicium parium ſuorum.</hi> He will neither diſplace nor diſgrace any Perſon, but by the Legal Tryal of his Peers, which is the true Legal Channel, and antient Fence againſt Arbitrary Government.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, Men of improvement, That's agreed with him for I am not for picking knots in Ruſhes.</p>
            <p>And now having ſhewed the poſitive Qualifications, he comes unto the Negatives: And</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Not thoſe who with as much Defiance as Error aſſert the Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Houſe of Commons began by Rebellion, 49. <hi>H.</hi> 3. And that they were not till then an Eſſential or Conſtituent part of the Legiſlative Power of the Kingdom. For my part I know none that have done it more or in better terms than this Perſon in the words juſt recited. I perceive this Gentleman is a meer whiffler; for without Reflection, It being no diſhonour to know the true Original either of things or perſons, had he been converſant with <hi>Selden, Cambden,</hi> or any other Antiquary, he would have found them no vilifiers of the Houſe of Commons, and yet they allow that Houſe no higher a pedigree than <hi>H.</hi> 3. and Mr.
<hi>Prinn,</hi> who was the moſt violent Aſſertor even of the Sovereignty of Parliaments, in his Book which bears that Title, and who ranſacked all the Records in the <hi>Tower,</hi> and in the <hi>Cotton Library,</hi> and all other places; yet could not raiſe the water a hairs breadth higher than the ſpring; and if he could have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced any Evidence of the Commons being a Conſtituent Part of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament before <hi>Hen.</hi> 3. he would not have been ſparing to acquaint us with it.</p>
            <p>But for his Certain Note, that is ſo worthy a particular Obſervation, that ſuch men only aim at the Deſtruction and Ruin of both, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I think it is beyond Aiming, and worthy a particular Obſervation, That they who cryed up the Houſe of Commons as the Parliament, as I have obſerved to you this Libeller doth, <hi>Pag.</hi> 13. where he talks of not conſidering to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:97679:6"/>chuſe a Parliament, making that part the people chuſe indefinitely the Par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liament, I ſay they were ſuch as he that voted the Honourable Houſe of Lords uſeleſs and dangerous, turned them out of Doors, depriving the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of their ſupream Court of Judicature, and ſetting up the moſt Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary and Deſpotical power under the name of Parliament that <hi>England</hi> ever ſaw, thereby ruining the famous Conſtitution of Parliaments.</p>
            <p>Certainly, they are the true Lovers of the Government, who give to every Degree and Order among us their proper due, not diminiſhing one to augment the other, which is the true healthful Temperament of the Body Politick.</p>
            <p>Then he falls into a great fit of Modeſty,<note place="margin">Pag. 12.</note> he will not with Effrontery conclude, but he tells the people of ſome that cry up an abſolutely abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute power in the Prince, that we are all Slaves, or Vaſſals, that <hi>voluntas Regis</hi> is
<hi>Lex Populi;</hi> why does he not name them, that they may receive their deſerved puniſhment? if he cannot do it, and I am ſure he would if he could, He is the Author, and publiſher of this Arbitrary Doctrine, and the diſperſer of a Defamation of his Sovereign: And if Malice and Art were not mingled in him to perfection, why could he not as well have told the people that his preſent Majeſty ſays the ſame as his Royal Father did, that he that will Preach more than he can prove, let him ſuffer: And cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly had there been as loyal Preaching in Schiſmatical Conventicles, of which with his large principles he is ſo great a Patron, and Advocate, as there hath conſtantly for Twenty years laſt paſt been in all the Churches of
<hi>England,</hi> and more particularly in <hi>White-hall</hi> Chappel, we ſhould have had no need of his Advice to ſave <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His ſecond and third Head are Co-incident,<note place="margin">Pag. 13,</note> a Declamation againſt Cakes and Ale, and would you think, that Cakes and Ale, and roaſt Beef ſhould be ſuch dangerous unqualifying things in an Election? why, I will unfold the Myſtery, the zeal of his party, and the underhand bearing their Charges he knows will carry them to Elections; And indeed they dare not offend their Teachers, who have them in as much awe as the Jeſuites have their Miſſioners. But the other party of whom they are afraid, who do not love the Trouble, and the rudeneſs of their Opponants at Elections, and had rather be minding their Affairs, do by the prevalency of Cuſtom expect to have their Charges defrayed; And methinks this croſſes one of his former Qualifications of ſuch as will propagate the Improvement, and Conſumption of the Growth of their Countrey; I aſſure you the Manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facture of good <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ale, Beef and Bread are ſtrangely help'd off at all Elections, and the good Towns rejoyce as much at a Diſſolution in hopes of the Advantages of Elections, as he ſeems to Lament.</p>
            <p>His fourth, is a Satyr againſt Penſioners; But leaſt that ſhould not hold water, in comes Reputed Penſioners: like Papiſts and Popiſhly affected; This ſweeps all, how many worthy Gentlemen have their Reputation blaſted with this ſcandal. It is the hardeſt caſe in the World ſure, that ſuch Loyal Gentlemen as ſpent their Eſtates in defence of their King, Countrey, Laws, Liberties and Religion cannot receive the favour of their Prince, but they muſt be branded with the Infamous name of Penſioners, and Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to their Countrey. I think indigent perſons as unqualified as he does, but I have learnt to diſtinguiſh between Indigent by Loyalty, and Indigent by Prodigality, the laſt I abominate, the firſt I pity.</p>
            <p>But by no means choſe a Courtier, or <hi>Durante beneplacito</hi> Man, and why I pray Sir? It is a Crime to be a Courtier? in former Parliaments thoſe who were Courtiers had the Honour to ſit always near Mr. <hi>Speakers</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:97679:7"/>Chair. And if he were as well acquainted with Parliamentary Records as he pretends to be with Qualifications, he would find many Orders even in 40. and 41. wherein the honourable Gentlemen that ſit next the Chair, are deſired to repreſent the Affairs of the Houſe to His Majeſty. Cannot a Man ſerve his King and his Countrey too, are their Intereſts ſo oppoſite as you make People believe? It was never good World ſince this was Preached for good Doctrine, nor ever will be till this State Hereſie is condemned by a Parliament, which I will not deſpair to live to ſee; but the wonder to me is to ſee the Confidence of the Jugler, firſt to topp upon us that this is no Reflection upon the King, and at the ſame caſt of his hand to ſlur the old Quick-ſilver Dy of Coordinacy of Power. The King being One Part of the Government ſhould leave the other free: But the Sophiſter never tells the People what part he is; but to ſupply his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, I will from the great Oracle of the Law the Lord <hi>Coke</hi> inform them, That the King is <hi>Caput, Finis, &amp; Principium Parliamenti,</hi> the
<hi>Alpha,</hi> and <hi>Omega,</hi> the Head, the End and Beginning of Parliaments; He is their Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain from whence they ſpring, and the Sea of Power, into which they run and devolve themſelves. As for His Admonition about Non Reſidents; I believe there are ſome who live about the Town who will give him little thanks for his Caution, eſpecially the Gentlemen of the Long Robe upon whom this is a ſour and ſevere Reflection.</p>
            <p>As few Minors as he can hinder, tho the Houſe of Commons hath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly had the Reputation of a great School of Wiſdome, which he ſeems to leſſen by this Reflection: And he might have added no <hi>bis Pueris</hi> if he had pleaſed, I ſhould not have quarrel'd him for it.</p>
            <p>The ſame I ſay as to Prodigals and Voluptuous Perſons.</p>
            <p>No Zealots for a Popiſh Succeſſor, I am none, nor know any ſuch, and wiſh he would diſtinguiſh between Succeſſor, and Popiſh Succeſſor, I do not find, that Chriſt or His Succeſſors the Apoſtles, were branded for Zealots for Heathen Succeſſors, becauſe they never endeavoured to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude them, but Taught, Commanded and Practiſed all Obedience to them. And certainly we ſhould have had none but State-Martyrs, if this Doctrin had been known to
<hi>Tertullian,</hi> to <hi>Julian the Apoſtate</hi>'s Soldiers, or the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Chriſtians. I have learnt to obey, and not diſpute the Determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of Kings and Parliaments, and can acquieſce in their definitive Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence. But becauſe this Gentleman hath ſo recommended Queen
<hi>Elizabeth</hi> in his Poſtſcript, and there as in his whole Libel, with deſign to reflect upon His Majeſty, I will ſhew him the Pourtraict of that Queens de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanor in a parallel Caſe of Succeſſion, by which the People ſhall ſee, it is no ſuch Tragical Thing for a Proteſtant Prince to deny the Importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities of a Parliament in the point of Succeſſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whereas Princes words do enter more deeply into Mens ears and minds,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cambd. Eliz. An. 1566.</note> 
               <hi>take theſe things from our Mouth. I that am a lover of the ſimple Truth, have ever thought you likewiſe to be ingenious Lovers of the ſame, But I have been deceived; For I have found that in this Parliament, Diſſimulation hath walked up and down masked under the vizard of Liberty, and Succeſſion; of your number, ſome there are, which have thought that Liberty to diſpute of the Succeſſion, and to eſtabliſh the ſame, is forthwith, either to be granted or denyed. If we had granted it, theſe Men had had their deſire, and had Triumphed over us. And if we had denyed it, they thought to have moved the hatred of our People againſt us, which our mortalleſt Enemies could never yet do. But their wiſdom was unſeaſonable, and their Counſels were haſty, neither did they fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee the Event. Yet hereby we have eaſily perceived who incline towards us,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:97679:7"/>and who are adverſe unto us. And we ſee, that your whole Houſe may be divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into four ſorts. For ſome have been Plotters, and Authors, ſome Actors; which with ſmooth words have perſuaded, ſome which have conſented being ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced with ſmooth words, and ſome which have been ſilent, admiring ſuch Bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; And theſe certainly are the more excuſable. Do ye think that we neglect your Safety, and ſecurity by the Succeſſion? or that we have a will to infringe your Liberty? Be it far from us, we never thought it. But indeed we thought good to call you back, when ye were running into the Pit. Every thing hath its fit ſeaſon; ye may peradventure after us have a wiſer Prince; but a more lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving towards you, ye ſhall never have. For our part, whether we may ſee ſuch a Parliament again, we know not: But for you, take ye heed, leſt you provoke your Princes Patience; nevertheleſs, of this be aſſured, that we think very well of moſt of you, and do imbrace every one of you, with our former kindneſs, even from our Heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to proceed, Not ſuch, ſays he, as play the Proteſtants in deſign,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>p.</hi> 17.</note> but are indeed diſguiſed Papiſts. They have induſtriouſly fixed the names of Maſqueraders, and diſguiſed Papiſts upon all ſuch Gentlemen as are zealous for the Church of <hi>England</hi> as now by Law eſtabliſhed, both againſt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, and Schiſmaticks, who according to Dr. <hi>Oates</hi> his Evidence, were to be aſſiſtant to the carrying on the Plot, <hi>Ibid.</hi> p. 67. by ſeditious Preachers ſet up, ſent out, maintained and directed what to Preach in their own or other private or publick Conventicles; And 'tis ſuch Maſquerade Jeſuits as this Libeller, that laugh at the Plot, diſgrace, and diſ-believe the Kings Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, in this ſo evident, and conſiderable a particular; That if ever Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery comes into <hi>England,</hi> it muſt come in like the
<hi>Trojan</hi> Horſe by him mentioned <hi>Milite Plenus,</hi> by breaking down the Walls of the Church by Toleration, the Gates being too narrow to let it in.</p>
            <p>But he goes on, and is not content to blaſt a few, but like a Contagion or Peſtilence, endeavours to ſweep away a whole Nation, with the Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Brand of <hi>Iriſh</hi> underſtanding, and Tories. A Tory is a Rebel, an Out-law, a Robber, and Murderer, and is a Name and Character that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly fits himſelf, who is ſo notorious a Robber of his Prince, and Murderer of the Reputation of ſo many worthy and innocent Gentlemen as he hath indeavoured to Defame.</p>
            <p>Whoever have been Neutrals in the grand Conteſt between Popery and Proteſtant Religion, and particularly in that Branch of it before recited, let them be rejected, for I joyn with him in opinion; That they, who are not with the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and the Government as now by Law eſtabliſhed, are againſt us, and that theſe only wait the good Hour, when they may ſafely ſhew their Teeth, and bite, which now like this Libeller, in Policy they hide with all the Artifice Imaginable.</p>
            <p>For his laſt Qualification of ſuch as have obſtructed Parliamentary pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, by unſeaſonable and unreaſonable inſiſting upon un-Parliamentary Priviledges, he muſt unriddle it, for it is un-underſtandable by the People, and therefore he might have left it unwrit, unprinted, unpubliſhed, and unrecommended by his Letter which hath another UN in it,
<hi>viz.</hi> To Undo the Nation.</p>
            <p>His Concluſion is like his Premiſſes, Canting, and Cunning, without either Truth or Honeſty,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>p.</hi> 18.</note> and ſo I leave him to the more juſt Animadverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Laws, and his Superiors, with this Recommendation that no man hath more artificially endeavoured to ruin the freedome of Elections, more maliciouſly Calumniated His Majeſty and the Government, nor more wickedly laboured to alienate the Affections of the People from their So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigns
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:97679:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>and by Seditious Forgeries to bring all the Calamities of a Civil War and Ruin upon the Nation.</p>
            <p>For his Poſtſcript, I could give him ſome hints of the Courage of Q. <hi>Eliz.</hi> mentioned by <hi>Cambden,</hi> Lord <hi>Coke,</hi> and others, but I am not for making or enlarging Breaches, and I wiſh he were of the ſame mind. I will only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend to him by way of ſupplicant what our Law ſuppoſes the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Qualification for perſons to be Elected Repreſentatives of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, for the Preſervation of His Majeſties Perſon, the Security of the Proteſtant Religion, and the Government, which would have ſpared him all his pains, and carries the ſtamp of Authority with it; It is the Proem of the Act of Parliament of the Thirteenth of <hi>Car.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. An Act for Preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of His Majeſties Perſon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="Act">
                        <p>THE Lords and Commons aſſembled in Parliament deeply weighing and conſidering the Miſeries and Calamities of well nigh twenty years, before your Majeſties Happy Return, and withall reflecting upon the Cauſes and Occaſions of ſo great, and deplorable Confuſions, do in all Humility and Thankfulneſs Acknowledge your Majeſties Incomparable Grace, and Goodneſs to your People, in your Free and General Pardon, Indempnity, and Oblivion, by which your Majeſty hath been pleaſed to deliver your Subjects not only from the Puniſhment, but alſo from the Reproach of their former Miſcarriages; which unexemplacy Piety and Clemenry of your Majeſty hath inflamed the Hearts of us your Subjects with an ardent deſire to expreſs all poſſible zeal, and duty in the Care and Preſervation of your Majeſties Perſon (in whoſe Honour and Happineſs conſiſts the Good and Welfare of your People) and in preventing (as much as may be) all Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable add Seditions Practices, and Attempts for the time to come. And becauſe the Growth and Increaſe of the late Troubles and Diſorders did in a very great Meaſure proceed from a Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of Seditious Sermons, Pamphlets, and Speeches daily Preached, Printed, and Publiſhed, with a tranſcendent Boldneſs defaming the Perſon and Government of your Majeſty and your Royal Father, wherein men were too much encouraged and (above all) from a wilful miſtake of the Supreme and Lawful Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, whilſt men were forward to cry up and maintain thoſe Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and Ordinances, Oaths and Covenants, to be Acts legal and warrantable, which in themſelves had not the leaſt Colour of law or Juſtice to ſupport them, of which kind of Diſtempers, as the preſent Age is not wholly freed, ſo Poſterity may be apt to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapſe into them, if a timely Remedy be not provided. We There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, &amp;c.</p>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </q>
            <p>Now whether this Libeller doth not fall within the deſcriptions of this Proem as well as many others have done of late, and whether they will not all come within the compaſs of the Act in point of Puniſhment is not my buſineſs to determin, I will only recommend to his and all honeſt mens Conſideration a piece of <hi>Solomons</hi> Wiſdom to cloſe with all in
<hi>Engliſh</hi> as he hath fronted his with Latin.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe ſix things doth the Lord hate, yea ſeven are an abomination to him, a proud look, a lying tongue, and hands that ſhed innocent blood; an heart that deviſeth wicked immaginations, feet that be ſwift in running into miſchief, a falſe witneſs, that ſeaketh lyes; and him that ſoweth diſcord among Brethren.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
